（雪(ゆき)たち）ええっ？
Huh?!
Hikari...
（雪）ひかり！
（町(まち)）キスした経験が…
You've kissed someone before?
（早紀絵(さきえ)）ウフ
Yep.
（ひかり）うん！
（町）あっ そ… それで
S-So...
Who was it?
（雪）相手は？
Mr. T!
（ひかり）先生
（ブッ！）
ほっぺに
On the cheek.
Oh, just on the cheek?
（雪）なんだ ほっぺか
My little sister kisses my cheek a lot, too.
私も妹に よくされるしな
On his cheek, huh?
（町）
ほっぺたか
でも ちょっと羨ましい
I'm still a little jealous.
（ひかり）エヘヘ　ビックリした？
Did I surprise you?
But why?
（雪）でも どうして？
He asked me all kinds of questions about vampires,
（ひかり）
先生が バンパイアのこと
いろいろ聞くから
イタズラしたの
so I did it as a joke.
Oh...
（町）へえ
ハア〜
I'm so jealous!
いいな〜！
♪〜
I want to talk...
About your Wonderful Original
Interviews with Monster Girls
The class is astir
I want to let myself go too,
But I end up putting on a fake smile.
Your eyes alone conveyed a competitive spirit
Biting at your lip forcefully.
You once said,
"I wouldn't want to worry what someone thinks
And end up hurting someone else in the process!"
When the chime rings out, as the rain lifts up,
We'll pass the boundaries of our school!
Jumping through the puddles, light will scatter about
Our smiles, and wishes will be so bright!
I want to talk...
About your Wonderful Original!
〜♪
（テレビ:シュン）
ユリコ…
Yuriko, I'm in love with—
Kyouko, can you check the water in the bath?
（町の母）京子(きょうこ)ちゃ〜ん
ちょっと
お風呂のお湯を見てくれる？
Don't say it.
Why not?
It's no good now... I can't be with you.
Oh, sure!
（町）あっ は〜い
I can't trust you anymore, Shun.
（テレビ:ユリコ）
私 もう シュン君のこと
信じられない
You have someone else now.
だって シュン君には あの人が
The Dullahan Surpasses Space-Time
But it isn't me she loves. It's my money!
（テレビ:シュン）
あいつが好きなのは 俺じゃない
俺の財産なんだ
But you told me you loved her!
Mom, the water's ready, so I'm turning it off!
お母さ〜ん
お風呂沸いてるから 止めとくね
Can you honestly say that wasn't true?
Okay, thanks.
（町の母）そう ありがとう
Look me in the eye and say it!
Hikari said she kissed Mr. Takahashi
（町）
ひかりちゃんは
高橋(たかはし)先生を困らせたくて
The only one I really love is you, Yuriko.
as a joke, to shake him up a bit.
イタズラでキスしたって
言ってたし
I'm sure he took it as a joke, too.
先生も きっと冗談として
受け止めたんだろうな
Shun...
Yuriko...
（２人）
んっ んん…
Then, wouldn't it also be okay for me to kiss him?
（町）
じゃあ 私がキスしても
いいんじゃないかな？
I just need to carry these, right?
（高橋）
これ 全部 運べばいいんですね？
Sorry to make you do all the heavy work.
（教頭）
力仕事を押しつけてしまって
すみません
It's no trouble...
（高橋）
いえいえ それだけが
取り柄みたいなものですから
In a way, that's all I'm good for.
アッハハハ
He certainly does good work for us, doesn't he?
（校長）
本当に よく頑張ってくれてますね
ええ
Yes.
He's even taken the initiative to offer counseling for our demi-human students.
亜人(あじん)の生徒たちの
カウンセリング役も
率先して やってくださって
Their parents are fond of him, too.
親御さんの評判も いいですし
That is true, but...
確かに そうですが
What's the matter?
（校長）どうされました？
Nothing.
いえ
That vice principal's such a jerk,
making me do all the heavy work.
（高橋）
まったく　教頭の野郎
重い荷物ばっか運ばせやがって
Being so beefy's getting to be a problem.
ガタイがいいのも考えもんだな
Mr. Takahashi!
（町）高橋先生
（高橋）ん？
Hey, Machi...
（高橋）おっ 町
Shall I help you?
お手伝いしましょうか？
ハハッ 大丈夫だよ　ありがとう
I'm fine. Thanks, though.
What's up?
何だ？　用事か？
Do you need... something?
うわっ！　どっ どうかしたか？
I-Is something wrong?
N-No, nothing's wrong.
（町）えっ いえ 別に
O-Okay, then.
そっ そうか
Is holding the head at eye level the "in" thing with dullahans now?
（高橋）
顔の高さを そろえるのが
デュラハンの間で
はやっているんだろうか？
Then again, Machi's the only dullahan in Japan.
いや デュラハンは
日本に町１人だしな
She must have some specific reason.
何か特別に意図が…
（町）ん〜
M-Mr. Takahashi...
た… 高橋先生
Y-Yeah? What is it?
（高橋）おっ おお　何だ？
M-Machi?
ま… 町？
I'm carrying heavy stuff right now, so this is dangerous...
今 重いものを持ってて 危ないから
な？　先に運んでからにしよう
Let me finish carrying these first.
I'm sure there's a reason you want to play around,
何か はしゃぎたい理由でも
あるんだろうが
but it's dangerous to hold your head with an unstable grip—
そんな不安定に
頭を抱えているのは 危な…
（町）あっ…
あ…
（高橋）あっ！
（高橋）ああっ！
（町）きゃ！
A-Are you all right?
だ… 大丈夫ですか？
You aren't... hurt, are you?
（高橋）ケガは ないか？
No, I'm fine.
はい 大丈夫です
That happens sometimes.
たまにあるんです こういうこと
But surprisingly, I can always catch it pretty easily.
でも 意外と簡単に
キャッチできるんですよ
So don't worry about—
だから 安心してくださ…
You thought I'd see that and not worry?!
安心して見ていられるわけが
ないだろう！
Someday, that pride could get you into a terrible accident!
そういった慢心が
いつか 取り返しのつかない事故に
つながるんだ
Be more careful!
気をつけろ！
あっ は…
あっ
I'm sorry. I... I didn't mean...
（町）うっ すみません
わっ 私 その…
Oh, uh, I just...
（高橋）いや その… な？
You see?
It's... It's my fault...
（町）
私… 私のせいで
散らかしてしまって
I made this mess.
And...
それで…
ウッ ウウ…
ウウッ
Machi...
（高橋）町
I'm so sorry!
（町）すみません　ごめんなさい！
And you can't straighten it while holding your head, right?
頭を抱えながらじゃ
うまく整理もできないよな
（すすり泣く声）
（足音）
Macchi? What's wrong?
（ひかり）マッチー？
（雪）どうしたの？
I see...
（雪）
そっか
高橋先生に怒られちゃったんだ
So Mr. Takahashi yelled at you.
（町）うん
Yeah.
You don't like being yelled at?
（ひかり）
マッチーは怒られるの嫌？
Huh? N-No...
（町）えっ？　う… うん
But it's more than that.
でも それ以上に
高橋先生は すごく優しい人
Mr. Takahashi is such a kind person.
So the idea that I got him angry makes me feel so awful...
なのに そんな人を
怒らせてしまった自分が
情けなくて 情けなくて…
I see... That makes sense.
そっか　そうだね
Here.
（ひかり）はい！
（雪）え？
Eh?
エヘッ
Wait here a sec!
ちょっと待ってて
（町）あっ ひかりちゃん？
Hikari?
I understand how you feel, Kyouko.
（雪）京子の気持ち 分かるよ
Mr. Takahashi really is a kind person.
高橋先生 本当に優しいもんね
Yeah.
（町）うん
Do you remember
（雪）少し前さ
when we all ate those popsicles together?
みんなでアイス食べたこと
覚えてる？
Huh? Yeah.
（町）え？　うん
I was worried about my nature as a snow woman.
（ひかり）
私 自分の性質に不安があって
When I told Mr. Takahashi about it,
その話をしたら 先生が
he tried something that actually brought out my nature.
私に あえて性質が
出るようなことをさせてね
To be honest, it wasn't easy.
正直 あれは つらかったな
I didn't understand why he'd put me through that.
どうして こんなつらいことを
私にさせるんだろうって…
But it cleared up my misunderstanding
でも そのおかげで誤解も解けて
and gave me the chance to be friends with you and Hikari.
こうして ひかりや京子と
友達になれたんだから
And I'm really grateful to him now.
今は すごく感謝してる
So, you know?
だから… ね？
I don't think being kind is only about coddling others.
ただ甘やかすだけが
優しいんじゃないと思う
He really cares about you, and he was honestly worried.
先生は 京子のことを
本当に思ってくれて
本気で心配したから
叱ってくれたんだよ
That's why he yelled at you.
Hey... Where are you taking me?
（高橋）
こら 俺をどこに連れてくんだ？
Just come on!
いいから いいから！
Wha?
（高橋）うお！
（町）せっ 先生！
M-Mr. Takahashi...
Okay, this time, you two are gonna have a real talk!
（ひかり）
じゃあ もっかい
ちゃんと先生と話そう
きゃ〜！　あっ あっ あっ！
フフフ　頭だけでは
逃げられないぞ マッチー
Your head can't run away on its own, Macchi.
Uh... I guess, um...
ああ… その なんだ
Machi, I shouldn't have done what I did. I'm sorry.
町 さっきは すまなかった
ごめん
（町）あ…
Scolding students is a necessary part of teaching.
（高橋）
叱るという行為は
教育上 必要なことだ
But there was no need to scold you at that time.
ただ さっきのお前には
叱る必要はなかった
I just got too emotional and yelled at you.
俺は ただ感情的に
どなりつけてしまっただけだ
Besides, I was partly to blame for what happened.
そもそも あのとき
俺にも非があった
We should have talked about it calmly.
一回 落ち着いて話すべきだったよ
I hope we can be friends again.
仲直りしてほしい
I'm really sorry.
本当に ごめんな
あっ そんな…
But...
That isn't something you need to apologize for.
高橋先生が
謝ることじゃないんです
I'm really sorry, too.
私も 本当に…
ごめんなさい
ヘヘッ
（町）えっ？
（高橋）どっ どうした？　町
Wh-What's wrong, Machi?
（町）ひひ… ひかりちゃんが
（高橋）ひかりが？
H-H-Hikari is...
Hikari?
ひえ〜い！　ふ〜！
お？　お？　へ〜い！
What are you doing to her?
な〜にやってるんだ お前は！
Mr. T, I don't think getting too emotional and yelling is good!
先生 感情的にどなるのは
よくないと思います
You keep doing things that call for scolding, despite constant warning!
お前は 何べん言っても
叱られることばっか
するだろうが！
（ひかり）あう…
So...
（高橋）
で？　結局 俺に
何がしたかったんだ？
What did you want from me, anyway?
Oh, that was...
（町）ああっ それは…
If I tell him I was trying to do what Hikari did,
（町）
ひかりちゃんのまねを
しようとしたって言ったら
would it make Hikari feel responsible?
ひかりちゃんが
責任 感じちゃうかな？
Heh heh.
エヘヘ
Heh heh!
エヘヘ！
"Aha ha," what?
（高橋）アハハ… 何だ？
A-Aha ha.
ア… アハハ
（町たち）プッ！　アハハハ！
What's with you guys?
（高橋）何なの？
（町たち）エヘヘ！　ウフフフ
（町）もう何なの…
（ひかり）アハハ
Interviews with Monster Girls
Do you feel itchy anywhere?
かゆいところは
ございませんか？　フフッ
ハア〜
I know Mr. Takahashi said otherwise,
高橋先生は ああ言ってくれたけど
but what I did was wrong...
悪いことしちゃったな
Hikari, Yuki, thanks for everything today.
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
Hikari, Yuki, thanks for everything today.
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
Hikari, Yuki, thanks for everything today.
To make it up to him, huh...
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
Hikari, Yuki, thanks for everything today.
To make it up to him, huh...
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
Hikari, Yuki, thanks for everything today.
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
How about a present?
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
How about a present?
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
How about a present?
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
How about a present?
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
How about a present?
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
How about a present?
Since I made Mr. Takahashi worry so much,
I want to do something to make it up to him. Any ideas?
To make it up to him, huh...
How about a present?
Wouldn't that just make him feel bad again?
You think so?
う〜ん
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
You think so?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
You think so?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
You think so?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
You think so?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
You think so?
Well, that's easy!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Hmm...
Not sure about a formal apology gift.
Isn't there anything else he'd like?
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
Well, that's easy!
There's only one thing that he'd
.like more than anything else!
One thing?
“アレ”？
M-Mr. Takahashi, would you like to know more about my body?
た… 高橋先生は
私の体のこと
知りたいと思いますか？
Yeah... I definitely would.
ああ すごく知りたい
But the fact
…が しかし
頭と体が分離していて
that you can maintain vital functions while head and body are separated
かつ 生命活動を
維持しているなんて
is such a huge deviation from common knowledge...
常識から逸脱しすぎていてな
Yes, that's true.
（町）そうですね
But I thought meeting you, someone who knows so much about demi-humans,
ただ 亜人について詳しい先生に
出会えたのは
might be a good chance to learn more about my own body.
改めて 自分の体について知る
いい機会だと思って…
Should we ask for another opinion?
別の人間の意見を聞いてみるか？
Huh?
（町）え？
I majored in biology.
俺の専攻は 生物学だった
Everything I know has its basis in that.
俺の言う常識は
そこに基づいている
So how about we ask someone who has a different kind of knowledge?
だから…
Musashino University of Science
別の常識の中で生きる人間に
聞いてみるのはどうだろう？
College looks so different from high school.
（町）
大学って 高校と随分 違いますね
It's so big, I'd probably get lost...
すごく広くて迷いそう
ハハ！　最初は そう感じるかもな
I guess it might feel that way at first.
Once you're there, you get used to it pretty fast.
入ると 意外と慣れるもんだ
Is the person we're seeing today a schoolmate of yours?
（町）
今日お会いするのは
ご学友の方で？
A schoolmate? Well, yeah, he is.
（高橋）
ご学友って…
いや 合ってるんだが
But after graduation, he stayed at the university to do research.
まあ そいつは卒業後も
大学に残って研究してるわけだ
He's a good guy, but he's a bit of an oddball.
いいヤツなんだが
ちょっと変わり者でな
An oddball?
（町）変わり者…
（高橋）ああ
Yeah.
I guess he's what you'd call a prodigy.
ああいうのを
天才肌って言うのかな？
Souma.
（高橋）相馬(そうま)
Hey.
よっ
Hey!
（相馬）
ハッハ！　テツ 久しぶりだな
Ha, Tetsu! It's been a long time!
ハハ！　相変わらず
表情１種類しかないな お前は
I see you still only have one expression.
What was that pause, I wonder.
今の間(ま)は 何だろう？
And you must be Machi?
そして 君が町君だね？
I'm Souma, a physics major. Nice to meet you.
僕は相馬だ
専攻は物理学だよ　よろしく
S-Same here... I'm Machi Kyouko.
あ… はい　町 京子です
Thank you for meeting with us today.
本日は よろしくお願いします
You don't have to be so formal.
あんまり かしこまらなくていいぞ
He's just a weirdo.
こいつ 変なんだからな
Ha! Harsh!
ハッハ！　辛辣(しんらつ)！
Hmm... However,
（相馬）う〜む しかし
meeting a real dullahan is quite an honor.
本物のデュラハンに
お目にかかれて光栄だね
Th-Thank you.
お… 恐れ入ります
物理学に身を置く者としては
As a man of physics,
a dullahan is the very definition of romance.
デュラハンという存在は
ロマンそのものだからね
Romance?
（高橋）ロマン？
Indeed! For instance, let's say Machi eats a steamed bun.
うむ　例えば 町君が
おまんじゅうを食べるとしよう
A steamed bun?
（町･高橋）おまんじゅう？
Machi puts the steamed bun in her mouth.
（相馬）
そのおまんじゅうは
町君が口に入れ
Steamed Bun
And when she swallows it,
そして 飲み込む その刹那！
it instantly teleports to her separate body!
瞬間的に分離した体のほうに
移動するわけだ
つまり これは
This is nothing short of
proof that transportation of matter beyond space-time is possible!
時空を超えた物質の移動が
可能であることの証明に
ほかならない！
Between Machi's head and body, there's a high-dimensional tunnel...
町君の頭と体は
高次元空間のトンネル
In other words, a wormhole, if I'm right.
つまり ワームホールで
つながっているのだろう
A wormhole?
ワームホール…
Oh, I've heard of those.
あっ あれか
In movies, they're the unexplained passages spaceships use to warp?
映画とかで 宇宙船が
ワープするときに通る—
よく分からん空間のことか
Yes, precisely. Occasionally called "hyperspace" in sci-fi works.
うむ そうだ
ＳＦだと
亜空間と呼ばれたりするな
What's it actually like inside a wormhole?
実際のワームホールの中は
どうなってるんだ？
High-dimensional space is entirely separate from our space-time rules.
高次元空間は
我々が生きる時空とは
理(ことわり)から まるで別物だからな
I can't definitely say,
何とも言えん
but the wormhole that connects Machi's head and body
ただ 町君の頭と体をつなぐ
ワームホールは
appears to be a fully established tunnel.
しっかり整備された
トンネルのようだ
After all, her nerves and blood vessels are all connected,
何せ 神経系やら血管やらも
全てがつながっていて
首の役割を
しっかり果たしているのだからな
so it successfully fulfills the role of a neck!
（高橋）う〜ん 首の役割
The role of a neck...
Yeah, I guess it would have to.
そりゃ果たせるだろうな
That's true.
（町）そうですね
（相馬）というと？
By which you mean...
This part of Machi... Her neck?
町のな この部分… 首？
The part you call a wormhole...
お前の言うワームホールの部分だが
It really does exist.
実は ちゃんと存在してるんだ
It exists, and it connects her head to her body.
存在して 町の頭と体を
つないでいる
（相馬）はっ！　どこに？
（町）わっ
Where?!
Uh, I'm not exactly sure.
えっと よく分からんが
But it's like her neck exists in a separate space...
首の部分だけ別の空間… にあって
Like, her neck itself is the wormhole.
首自体がワームホールになっている
Hmm...
（相馬）ふむ
（町）ああ…
I don't doubt you, but on what grounds do you say this neck exists?
疑うわけではないが
首が存在するという根拠を
聞いてもいいか？
うん 俺は 町がしゃべるってことは
首があるんだろうなって思った
I think the fact that Machi talks means that she has a neck.
Humans can't speak without vocal cords.
声帯がなきゃ 人はしゃべれない
So I asked Machi...
それで 町に聞いてみたんだ
A long time ago, I was checked with an endoscope, and they did find a neck.
昔 胃カメラで見てみたら
首の部分が ちゃんとあって
I see! So you do have a neck!
（相馬）
うむ！　どうやら首はあるようだ
Then, based on what things
つまり 胃カメラ等で見るかぎりは
町君は 普通の人間と
何ら変わりないわけだ
like endoscopes show, you're no different than an ordinary human.
Yes, that's what the doctor said, too.
はい お医者さんも
そうおっしゃっていました
Though, that would be a pretty tiny wormhole...
しかし ワームホールも
随分と こぢんまりしてきたな
Ha! No, in fact,
ハッハ！　いや むしろ
町君のワームホールのほうが
it could be said that Machi's wormhole is highly sophisticated!
高度に制御されていると
言えるかもしれないぞ
May I summarize?
（相馬）少し まとめてみても？
（高橋）ああ
Sure.
Essentially, Machi is no different from an ordinary human,
町君は 基本的に
普通の人間と変わりないが
but her neck exists in a separate space,
首の部分だけ 別の空間に存在し
forming a wormhole that connects her head and body.
頭と体がつながる
ワームホールになっていると…
In this case, the separate space would be high-dimensional space.
この場合 別の空間とは
すなわち 高次元空間
Theoretically, that'd make even time travel possible.
理論的には
タイムトラベルすら実現できる
I would love to see how it works with my own eyes...
どのようなものなのか？
ぜひ この目で
直接 見てみたいものだが
ん？
Forgive me for waiting until now to ask,
今更ながらで 恐縮だが
but what do the joints of your "neck" look like?
その首の結合部分というのは
どうなっているんだい？
Oh, both sides are enclosed in skin.
（町）
あっ どちらも
皮膚で覆われています
（相馬）皮膚！
Skin!
It sure is strange.
不思議だよな
What goes in your mouth ends up in your body,
口を通ると 体に たどりつくが
but from outside, the pathway looks closed.
外から見ると 道は塞がれている
Maybe someone's trying to hide that pathway.
誰かが その通り道を
隠そうとしているんですかね？
Oh? Who would that mischief-maker be?
お？　ハハッ
誰だ？　そのイタズラ好きは
Hikari?
ひかりか？
To say that someone's hiding it is quite fitting.
（相馬）
“隠そうとしている”とは
言い得て妙だ
High-dimensional space definitely exists,
高次元空間は 確かに存在している
but it's impossible to observe, almost as if someone is hiding it.
隠蔽されていると思えるほどに
その存在を観測することはできない
Once food enters her mouth, the process works like any human's,
口を通れば
普通の人間と変わりないし
and from outside, it's closed off.
外から見れば 蓋がされている
Why can't it be observed? Was that someone's intention?
なぜ観測できないのか？
誰かの意思だろうか？
Intention... Observation...
意思　観測…
Mr. Souma?
（町）相馬先生？
（高橋）町
Machi...
Shh.
（高橋）し〜っ
Is Mr. Souma thinking right now?
（町）相馬先生 考え中ですか？
Yeah.
（高橋）ああ
His expression never changes, so it's almost like time's stopped, huh?
表情 変わらないから
本当に時間が止まったみたいだろ？
He really is unusual.
（町）変わった人ですね
Yep.
（高橋）ああ
I guess unusual people are unusual, whether they're demis or not.
（町）
デミとか関係なく
変わってる人は変わってるんですね
I guess so.
（高橋）そうだな
（相馬）んん！
（町）ああっ！
All phenomena occur for a reason.
現象には 原因がある
In physics, long ago,
かつて 物理学では
観測という行為は
observation wasn't considered a sufficient cause of phenomena.
現象の原因たりえないと
考えられていた
Observation?
（高橋）観測？
Basically, whether humans see something or not...
つまり 人間が
観測しようがしまいが
Or to take it further,
もっと言えば 人間が この宇宙に
存在していなかったとしても
whether humans exist in this universe...
The results of phenomena would be the same.
現象の結果に変わりはない
ということだ
Right.
（高橋）う〜ん
That seems like an obvious conclusion to me...
それが 当たり前のように
思えますが
But wait just a minute!
ところが どっこい！
Some circumstances change due to human observation!
人間が観測することによって
状態が変化するものがあるのだ！
な… それは 一体？
What would those be?
In a world where a single electron can be observed,
電子１粒がどうの
という世界における
there's a thing called a "quantum"!
量子と呼ばれるものだ
Before it is observed, a quantum expands like space, in a wave-like pattern.
観測される前の量子は
波の性質を持った状態で
空間的な広がりを持っている
しかし！
However, when observed, it instantly contracts into particles!
観測されることで
１点に収縮し 粒となるのだ
Waves?
波…
Particles?
粒…
ハア〜 よく分からん
I don't get it.
Is that true?
そうなんですか…？
（相馬）
ハッハ！　いいリアクションは
またの機会に取っておくとして
We'll save the good reactions for another time!
Basically, I'm trying to say that the act of observation has its own meaning.
要は 観測という行為は
何か特別な意味がありそうだ
…と言いたかった
In terms of the phenomena I spoke of,
先ほどの現象の話で言えば
human observation can change the result of a phenomenon.
人間が観測することで
現象の結果は変わるということだ
Does it not give you a sense of the necessity of humans in the universe?
この宇宙に人間がいる必然性を
感じないだろうか？
Ooh...
（高橋）おお！
（町）それは すごいです
That is impressive!
And what is observation?
そして 観測とは何か？
An act!
行為だ！
Behind every act is human intention.
行為の裏には 人間の意思がある
In other words, human intention influences all phenomena!
つまり 人間の意思は
現象に影響を及ぼす！
Ooh!
おお！
It's like a supernatural ability!
超能力みたい
And that's what came to mind after I spoke with Machi.
（相馬）
というようなことを
町君と話していて思った
I get it... By that logic,
（高橋）
なるほど　その理屈で言えば
a snow woman's ability to freeze matter, using negative emotions,
雪女も ネガティブな感情によって
物質を冷やすサイキック
could also be called a psychic power.
という見方もできるわけか
Regarding the joints of Machi's neck...
町君の首の接合部分についてだが
Hey, no trying to look in... It's embarrassing for her.
（高橋）
ああ 恥ずかしがるから
のぞき込むのは なし
And touching it seems to hurt her, so don't.
触るのも つらいみたいだからダメ
Ha! Blocked by her management!
ハッハ！　事務所ＮＧ！
Normally, something far removed from the rules of our own space-time
その部分は 本来
我々の生きる時空の理とは異なる
何かが観測されてしかるべきだが
would be observable in that part of her.
But a glance reveals it's covered with skin.
見ると 皮膚で覆われている
Who's hiding that something?
何かを隠すのは誰か？
Most likely, the answer is we are.
その答えは 恐らく我々だ
When we try to observe a thing's existence,
何かが存在する点を
我々が観測しようとすると
our intention to observe it causes a change in that thing.
観測しようとする意思が
何かの状態に変化を与え
蓋をしてしまうのだ
That sounds like what you said earlier about the quantum.
さっきの量子の話と似てるな
More like I was just imitating that.
（相馬）
というよりも それをまねただけだ
And finally, that flame!
（相馬）そして 最後に その炎！
（町）ああっ
I believe it is not a flame, but a fluctuation in space.
それは 炎というより
空間の揺らぎのようなものだと思う
It's the only thing reminiscent of an observable separate space.
我々が観測できる
唯一の別空間らしさだ
And when someone tries to touch it, an adverse reaction occurs.
そして 人間が触れると
拒否反応が出たり
It appears that its appearance changes with your emotions, yes?
見るところ 感情によって
形状が変化したりもするらしいね
Uh, yes...
あっ はい
That may be the proof that human observation influences phenomena!
（相馬）
それこそが 人間の意思が
現象に影響を及ぼす—
証左なのかもしれない
Dullahans can perform relocations of matter that surpass space-time,
デュラハンは 時空を超えた
物質の移動を実現し
and they hint at the physical significance of human intention!
かつ 意思の物理的意味を
示唆している
デュラハンは
物理の可能性そのものだ！
The dullahan is the potential of physics!
I'm done.
終わり
Good show. That was a lot of fun.
（高橋）
お疲れ　楽しかった 楽しかった
What about you, Machi? Did you think it was fun?
町はどうだ？　面白かったか？
（町）ハア…
It was incredibly fun.
すごく面白かったです
How did you two get to know each other?
（町）
お２人は
どう知り合ったんですか？
We sat next to each other in a lecture.
（高橋）共通の講義で 席が隣でな
Yep.
（相馬）うむ
He hasn't changed. He's still a romanticist.
こいつは 昔から変わらん
ロマンチストだ
He wants to remove the "fiction" from "science fiction."
サイエンスフィクションから
フィクションを取りたいんだ
Ha! A funny way of putting it.
ハッハ！　面白い表現だ
But you've changed, Tetsu.
そういうテツは 変わったよ
Have I?
（高橋）そうか？
Every time I see you, you look more muscular!
（相馬）
会うたびに
ムキムキになっていくじゃないか
You meant my looks?
（高橋）見た目かよ
（着信音）
（町）あっ
Pardon me for a moment.
（町）
すみません　ちょっと失礼します
おう
Thanks for doing this, Souma.
今日はありがとな 相馬
Not at all. It was an intriguing experience for me, too.
なに 僕も興味深い経験を
させてもらった
本当は 町に起こっていることを
もっと調べたいんじゃないか？
But you want to look into what's going on with Machi more?
Well, of course I do.
まあ それはそうだ
But you know better than anyone how difficult
だが 亜人を対象とした
研究の難しさは
researching demi-humans is, do you not?
テツが いちばん
よく知っているだろう？
（高橋）ふん 倫理がなんだ
Screw ethics.
If the subject's okay with it, what's the problem?
当事者がオーケーなら
それでいいじゃねえか
Ha! You sound just like you did when you were a student.
ハッハ！
学生のころみたいになってるぞ
Personally, I like this conservative world we live in.
まっ 僕は これくらい保守的な
世の中でいいと思うがね
Mr. Souma said I shouldn't aimlessly accept that I'm a dullahan.
（町）
デュラハンであることを
漫然と受け入れるのはよくないと
お話を伺ったけれど
But watching him
相馬先生を見て
made me think I shouldn't go about my studies aimlessly, either.
勉強も漫然とやっているだけでは
ダメなんだなと思った
For me, studying is like taking a quiz.
私にとって 勉強は
クイズのようなもの
There are problems, and I answer them.
問題があって答える
それで満足していた
1st
Machi
Kyouko
2nd
Tachibana
Aoi
I was content with that.
But I was wrong. There's more beyond that.
でも 違うんだ
その先があるんだ
Things that could change the world.
世の中を変えるような何かが…
One of those things is the secret of dullahans,
その１つがデュラハンの秘密で
私は それを知りたい
and I want to know what it is.
If researching dullahans is difficult on an ethical level, then...
ほかの人が
デュラハンを研究するのは
倫理的に難しいのだとすれば…
Maybe I could become a researcher and research dullahans myself.
私自身が研究者になって
デュラハンの研究をするのは
ありかな？
Yeah, right.
なんちゃって
You hear that?
聞いたか？
Yes!
ああ
The sight of a student gazing toward the future is so beautiful!
未来を見据える学生の姿は
かくも美しい
Incidentally...
ところで ここに
本校のパンフレットがあってだな
I have a pamphlet for our school here.
うっ 関わる気 満々じゃねえか
You really intend to get involved, don't you?
Okay, okay. I'll put in a good word.
分かった 分かった
よろしく言っておくよ
Of course, I know very well
まっ デュラハンという存在に
that you have a reason for being so eager to learn about dullahans.
お前が躍起になるだけの
理由があることは よく分かる
Naturally!
（相馬）当然だ！
If I can pinpoint high-dimensional space's behavior,
高次空間の振る舞いを
掌握できれば
warping and time travel may be possible!
ワープやタイムトラベルが
可能になるかもしれない
Now that I know human intention influences phenomena,
意思が現象に
影響を及ぼすと分かれば
supernatural power isn't just a dream!
超能力も夢じゃない！
（あくび）
（高橋）そうね
Yep...
Not to mention, if we knew the secret of dullahans,
そもそも デュラハンの秘密が
分かるということは
it may be possible for Machi to be a normal human.
町君が普通の人間になることも
可能かもしれない
Oh.
（高橋）
そうか
I guess that is possible...
そういうこともあり得るか
ああ なんだろうな
I don't know.
This is probably a "normal" look...
これが普通の姿なんだろうが
But it just doesn't feel right anymore.
もう違和感を覚えてしまうな
Those three would still be the same.
あいつらは相変わらずそうだ
ハハッ ただ 町が先輩みたいだ
Except that Machi would look like an older student.
Mr. Takahashi!
（町）高橋先生
（高橋）あっ
Please hug my head!
頭 ハグしてください
Please put my head in your lap!
頭 膝に乗せてください
（高橋）う〜ん
I guess ethics really are important.
倫理観って大事だな
Ah, it's Tetsu the responsible adult!
おっ 社会人のテツだ
ん？
フフッ
♪〜
The events of a mysterious world,
Like the ones you hear of in fairy tales,
Are actually closer than you think
Just like the way you and I met!
When I stood up tall to gaze at
The familiar scenery outside my window,
Even days that felt like torture seemed precious somehow.
Stuck in my heart, I can't put them into words
How should I try to put these feelings into words?
Laughing over stupid things...
Getting mad over small details...
We'll keep carving these trivial moments into our hearts.
Sometimes I'm feeling sad...
But when I'm with you, I'm so happy!
We'll keep on building these irreplaceable moments,
〜♪
And little by little, we'll come to understand one another.
Demis Want to Support
Next Time
（ひまり）
次回「亜人ちゃんは
語りたい」
Next time on Interviews with Monster Girls:
Demis Want to Support.
「亜人ちゃんは
支えたい」